Inventory of the Thomas C. Douglass Papers, 1941-1946
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Thomas C. Douglas Papers 1941-1946.
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
2007.21
25 folders.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
Purchase, 2007.
Biographical Information
Thomas C. Douglass was a physician from Wilmette, Illinois who served during WWII in both domestic and foreign locations including Colorado, Chicago, Michigan, North Carolina and Guadalcanal. They had a son, Tommy, who was born during wartime.
Scope and Content
Letters of Thomas C. Douglass, 1941-1946, relating to WWII. Letters to his wife Suzanne concerning family issues and war news. Includes descriptions of his medical practices and financial dealings.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged chronologically by date.
Index Terms
Persons:
Douglass, Suzanne Lyon Wallace, 1922-1999
Subjects:
United States. Army Medical Dept.; World War, 1939-1945--Medical care.; Medical Department, United States Army. Surgery in World War II.; Surgery in World War II.
Contents List
- September-November 1941 (Folder 1)
  Letters of Thomas C. Douglass to Suzanne Lyon from Colorado Springs, Colo. Personal letters to Sue. Professes his love. News of his dying father. Discusses possible future plans.
- August-September 1942 (Folder 2)
  Letters of Thomas C. Douglass to his wife Suzanne from Chicago, Nevada, and 48th Station Hospital, Fort Ord, Calif. Instructions on life insurance policies. Medical advice on Suzanne's pregnancy. Descriptions of daily routine. Request for popular books. Words of concern and love for the unborn child and the mother.
- February-March 1942 (Folder 3)
  Letters of Thomas C. Douglass to his wife Suzanne from 12th General Hosp, Camp Custer, Michigan. Complains of assignment to septic surgery instead of abdominal section. Expresses gratitude for Suzanne's visit.
- October-November 1942 (Folder 4)
  Letters of Thomas C. Douglass to his wife Suzanne from 48th Station General Hospital, San Francisco, Cal. Advice on pregnancy care and delivery. Promises to return home to see the baby soon.
- December 1942 (Folder 5)
  Letters of Thomas C. Douglass to his wife Suzanne from an undisclosed location in the South Pacific. Separately celebrates the 9th month of marriage. Requests for a camera to photograph surgical specimens and patients. Friend Burns and his wife Marion had a daughter. Reqeusts Suzanne to look for a home to buy. Advises on letter censorship and Requests not to spoil the newborn, Tommy.
- January-February 1943 (Folder 6)
  Letters of Thomas C. Douglass to his wife Suzanne from an undisclosed location in the South Pacific. Fixes anesthetic apparatus. Tommy turns four months old on Feb 19, 1943. Discusses Suzanne's desire to move. Receives the requested camera.
- March-April 1943 (Folder 7)
  Letters of Thomas C. Douglass to his wife Suzanne from an undisclosed location in the South Pacific. Suzanne moves from Wilmette to Chicago, Illinois. TCD in charge of surgery and a large ward. Schedules a complicated hand surgery. Estimates the war to end in three years.
- May-June 1943 (Folder 8)
  Letters of Thomas C. Douglass to his wife Suzanne from an undisclosed location in the South Pacific. Suzanne gets a dog. Sister sells the house. Mention of coal strike in the news. Holds the Congress responsible for unstable economy. TCD's Bronchitis develops into a small cold.
- July-August 1943 (Folder 9)
  Letters of Thomas C. Douglass to his wife Suzanne from an undisclosed location in the South Pacific. News of new landing of troops on Vella Lavella, expects Italy to drive out the Nazis. Expects to be home in about 1946. All the fish in the aquarium dies.
- September-October 1943 (Folder 10)
  Letters of Thomas C. Douglass to his wife Suzanne from an undisclosed location in the South Pacific. Tommy gets more teeth. Operates on an elbow to prevent hand paralysis. Expects to serve in the war until 1945 or 1946. News of Russia fighting Germans on the borders. Worries the possible extension of the war.
- November-December 1943 (Folder 11)
  Letters of Thomas C. Douglass to his wife Suzanne from an undisclosed location in the South Pacific. Suzanne joins Women's Faculty Club. Advises Suzanne to refrain from traveling and purchasing a house during wartime. Anticipates the victorious battles in Europe will speed up the war.
- January-February 1944 (Folder 12)
  Letters of Thomas C. Douglass to his wife Suzanne from an undisclosed location in the South Pacific. Victory in Europe slow. Military considers two-year rotation policy - possibility of a leave in one year.
- March-April 1944 (Folder 13)
  Letters of Thomas C. Douglass to his wife Suzanne from an undisclosed location. Celeberates the second wedding anniversary overseas. Operates on several cases of appendix. News of Russians near Chekoslovakia. New hospital opens. Two-year rotation policy still unclear. Anniversary of 18th month overseas.
- May-June 1944 (Folder 14)
  Letters of Thomas C. Douglass to his wife Suzanne from an undisclosed location. Encouraging news of the European invasion. Gives advice on finance and on Tommy's behavior.
- July-August 1944 (Folder 15)
  Letters of Thomas C. Douglass to his wife Suzanne from Guadalcanal. Rumors of the war in Europe ending. Russians fight Germans in the East. Still uses APO, but the military permits disclosure of the location. Operates amputation surgeries and treats few cases of severe burns.
- September-October 1944 (Folder 16)
  Letters of Thomas C. Douglass to his wife Suzanne from Guadalcanal. Rumors of the ending of the European war in two months. Possible addition of two more doctors to the hospital. Tommy has a birthday. News of successful US landing in the central Phillipines. 2nd anniversary of being overseas.
- November-December 1944 (Folder 17)
  Letters of Thomas C. Douglass to his wife Suzanne from Guadalcanal. Operates on the biggest abdominal case and few cases of hernias. The western front in Europe a slow progress. German offensive in Europe withdraws.
- January-February 1945 (Folder 18)
  Letters of Thomas C. Douglass to his wife Suzanne from Guadalcanal. Expects to come home before the year end. Russian advances on the eastern front in Europe. Suzanne moves to 226 Washington Avenue, Glenview, Illinois.
- March-April 1945 (Folder 19)
  Arrives at new base. President Roosevelt dies. Decides to take the leave over the chance of rotation - the assignment to domestic location.
- May 1945 (Folder 20)
  Letters of Thomas C. Douglass to his wife Suzanne from Guadalcanal. Grants a 45-day leave. The German war practically over.
- April-May 1946 (Folder 21)
  Letters of Thomas C. Douglass to his wife Suzanne from Moore General Hospital, Swananoa, N.C and Denver, Colorado. Suzanne has a mild health problem with her breasts. Expects to be home in four months. Suzanne fixes up the house in Wilmette. The President's address signals the possible ending of the war. Arranges for Suzanne's visit.
- June-July 1946 (Folder 22)
  Letters of Thomas C. Douglass to his wife Suzanne from Fitzsimons General Hospital, Denver, Colorado. TCD's x-rays come back negative. Requests his publications sent to Dr. Davis.
- August-September 1946 (Folder 23)
  Letters of Thomas C. Douglass to his wife Suzanne from Fitzsimons General Hospital, Denver, Colorado. Advice on finance. Progress on house remodeling. Arrangements for G.I. loan. Plans Suzanne's visit.
- 29 January 1943 (Folder 24)
  Letters of Thomas C. Douglass to his son Tommy. Words of love to Tommy and his mother.
- 1941-1944, no date (Folder 25)
  1) Letter of Adele to Suzanne from Italy dated June 23, 1944. Praises the new house and talks about Italian atmosphere. 2) Telegram of Thomas C. Douglass dated Nov 3, 1941 to his wife Suzanne, informing of arrival. 3) Unsigned New Year card from Thomas C. Douglass. 4) Burns's letter to Suzanne, informing Tom's condition.